<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>infectious-diseases | Brian D. Williamson, PhD</title>
    <link>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/tag/infectious-diseases/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://bdwilliamson.github.io/tag/infectious-diseases/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>infectious-diseases</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2014--2021 Brian D. Williamson</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2021 12:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/images/icon_huca44d5504774c48bc693dc9fda57798d_24945_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>infectious-diseases</title>
      <link>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/tag/infectious-diseases/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical inference and containerization in computational pipelines</title>
      <link>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/talk/fhbiostat2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2021 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/talk/fhbiostat2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Broadly Neutralizing Antibodies</title>
      <link>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/project/bnabs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/project/bnabs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The broadly neutralizing antibody VRC01, developed by the Vaccine
Research Center of the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious
Diseases, is currently being evaluated in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ampstudy.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Antibody Mediated
Prevention&lt;/a&gt; study (AMP). While the primary goal
of AMP is to assess the preventative efficacy of VRC01, a key secondary
goal is to determine if this efficacy differs based on characteristics
of the HIV virus. There are many possible locations on the HIV genome
that we might be interested in; if we simply did a statistical test for
association at each possible location, and then appropriately accounted
for this multiple testing, then we would have low power to detect
effects. To prepare for AMP, we used data on HIV viruses from the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hiv.lanl.gov/components/sequence/HIV/neutralization/main.comp&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Compile, Neutralize, and Tally NAb
Panels&lt;/a&gt;
database. Our goals were to: (i) develop a score that performed well for
predicting whether or not an HIV virus was sensitive to neutralization
by VRC01, and (ii) to identify groups of HIV genome features that were
important in predicting neutralization sensitivity. This project is
joint work with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/camagaret/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Craig Magaret&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.benkeserstatistics.com/#!&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;David Benkeser&lt;/a&gt;, Peter Gilbert,
and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We next extended the methods used for the VRC01 analysis to combinations
of antibodies – a prevention strategy involving multiple bnAbs is likely
to be much more effective than a strategy with a single bnAb. Sohail
Nizam joined the team for this project. The software is implemented as a
Docker container.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collaborative Science</title>
      <link>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/project/collaborative-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/project/collaborative-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;hiv-vaccines&#34;&gt;HIV vaccines&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;correlates-of-hiv-1-risk&#34;&gt;Correlates of HIV-1 risk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we do not yet have a broadly efficacious vaccine against HIV-1,
clinical trials of HIV-1 vaccine candidates can identify potential
correlates of risk or of protection. These correlates are measurable
signs that a person is at risk of or is protected from infection by
HIV-1, respectively. In this work, I collaborated with Peter Gilbert and
others affiliated with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hvtn.org/en.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;HIV Vaccine Trials
Network&lt;/a&gt; to analyze data from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hvtn.org/en/community/community-compass/vol19-issue1/hvtn-505-recap.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;HVTN
505&lt;/a&gt;
clinical trial. We identified three antibody features that inversely
correlated with HIV-1 infection risk. This may help in designing future
HIV-1 vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;surrogate-endpoints-for-cytomegalovirus-disease&#34;&gt;Surrogate endpoints for cytomegalovirus disease&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used a combination of classical statistical methods and ensemble-based machine learning to assess various viral load kinetics as potential surrogate endpoints for cytomegalovirus disease after transplant. We found that mean, peak, and change in viral load over the first five weeks of treatment fulfilled the Prentice criteria for surrogacy and captured a large proportion of the treatment effect in two randomized, controlled trials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;non-vaccine-hiv-prevention&#34;&gt;Non-vaccine HIV prevention&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;characteristics-associated-with-hiv-risk-in-young-south-african-women&#34;&gt;Characteristics associated with HIV risk in young South African women&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study is based on data from the HIV Prevention Trials Network
(HPTN) trial 068. In this work, we aimed to identify factors associated
with age-discordant partnerships (one partner greater than 5 years older
than the other) and examine the association between partner age
discordance and HIV risk in young South African women. We found that a
history of age-discordant partnerships is associated witih greater odds
of reporting HIV risk factors. This is joint work with &lt;a href=&#34;https://fmch.duke.edu/profile/tiarney-ritchwood&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tiarney
Ritchwood&lt;/a&gt;, Jim Hughes,
and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hiv-treatment-as-prevention&#34;&gt;HIV treatment as prevention&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HPTN 063 was a clinical trial that aimed to examine potential HIV
transmissions and the frequency of bacterial sexually transmitted
infection (STI) acquisition among an international group of HIV-positive
individuals in HIV care. The long-term goal was to inform
treatment-as-prevention programs and provide ways of evaluating the
potential impact of such programs. We found that there were substantial
numbers of both estimated HIV transmissions and STIs, despite sampling
individuals in HIV care. This suggested that augmenting secondary
prevention interventions may be a means to decrease HIV incidence. This
is joint work with &lt;a href=&#34;https://people.miami.edu/profile/sas436@miami.edu&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Steven
Safren&lt;/a&gt;, Jim Hughes,
and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;cancer-treatment&#34;&gt;Cancer treatment&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;optimizing-cancer-treatment-strategies-using-single-cell-data&#34;&gt;Optimizing cancer treatment strategies using single-cell data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this work, our goal was to develop an algorithm for optimally
assigning patients to cancer treatment strategies. We leveraged data
from single-cell mass cytometry to: automatically determine
subpopulations of cells; create a nested effects model to infer gene
hierarchy based on perturbation effects due to administered drugs; and
create a scoring and ranking algorithm that identifies the minimal
number of drugs among a combination of drugs with teh maximal desired
intracellular effects. This is joint work with &lt;a href=&#34;http://med.stanford.edu/plevritis.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sylvia
Plevritis&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://med.stanford.edu/plevritis.html/People&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Benedict
Anchang&lt;/a&gt;, and others.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical Methods for Clinical Trials</title>
      <link>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/project/clinical-trials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/project/clinical-trials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In settings where it is not ethical to perform a classical
placebo-controlled trial, new interventions must be evaluated against
the standard of care. Non-inferiority trials are often used to evaluate
new interventions in this context. Here, the goal is for the
experimental intervention to be “not unacceptably worse” than the
standard of care, so that there are an increased number of viable
intervention options. A common assumption in non-inferiority trials is
that the active control population (typically receiving standard of
care) is similar to the populations in prior placebo-controlled
randomized trials. However, if characteristics in the current trial
differ from previous trials – for example, adherence to the active
control regimen is lesser or greater than planned – then the chance of a
false positive result (type I error) or a false negative result (type II
error) can be different than planned. In this work, we proposed a method
for rigorously adapting a non-inferiority trial based on observed
characteristics of the active control participants. This is joint work
with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fredhutch.org/en/labs/profiles/donnell-deborah.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Deborah
Donnell&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fredhutch.org/en/labs/profiles/hanscom-brett.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Brett
Hanscom&lt;/a&gt;,
and Jim Hughes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guiding HIV-1 antibody regimen down-selection and prevention efficacy trial design using machine learning</title>
      <link>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/talk/hivde2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/talk/hivde2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
