<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>biostatistics | Brian D. Williamson, PhD</title>
    <link>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/tag/biostatistics/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://bdwilliamson.github.io/tag/biostatistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>biostatistics</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2014--2020 Brian D. Williamson</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/images/icon_huca44d5504774c48bc693dc9fda57798d_24945_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>biostatistics</title>
      <link>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/tag/biostatistics/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nonparametric variable importance assessment using machine learning techniques</title>
      <link>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/publication/journal-article/vim1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/publication/journal-article/vim1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We first focused on a nonparametric extension of the classical measure based on the difference in R-squared (from linear models). We provide a simple approach for estimation that incorporates machine learning tools, and yields valid confidence intervals for the true importance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microbial Abundance</title>
      <link>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/project/microbial-abundance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 16:54:42 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/project/microbial-abundance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this work, we propose a statistical method for combining inexpensive
(but often lower-quality) estimates of relative abundance (e.g.,
collected using universal primers for the 16S rRNA gene) and higher
quality (but often expensive) estimates of absolute abundance (e.g.,
from quantitative PCR) to estimate absolute abundance of all taxa.
Crucially, our proposal accounts for differences in the efficiency of
taxon detection in the relative and absolute abundance data. This is
joint work with 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://faculty.washington.edu/jphughes/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jim Hughes&lt;/a&gt;
and 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://statisticaldiversitylab.com/team/amy-willis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Amy Willis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variable Importance</title>
      <link>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/project/variable-importance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 10:58:17 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/project/variable-importance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is often of interest to understand the population interplay between
the outcome and measured covariates. Variable importance is a useful
tool towards this goal. Examples include: HIV vaccine studies,
correlates of risk analyses, and identifying patients at high risk of
returning to a hospital after discharge for heart failure. This is joint
work with 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://faculty.washington.edu/mcarone/about.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Marco
Carone&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fredhutch.org/en/labs/profiles/gilbert-peter.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Peter
Gilbert&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://faculty.washington.edu/nrsimon/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Noah Simon&lt;/a&gt;, and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jeanfeng.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jean Feng&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical Methods for Clinical Trials</title>
      <link>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/project/clinical-trials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 10:47:17 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/project/clinical-trials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In settings where it is not ethical to perform a classical
placebo-controlled trial, new interventions must be evaluated against
the standard of care. Non-inferiority trials are often used to evaluate
new interventions in this context. Here, the goal is for the
experimental intervention to be “not unacceptably worse” than the
standard of care, so that there are an increased number of viable
intervention options. A common assumption in non-inferiority trials is
that the active control population (typically receiving standard of
care) is similar to the populations in prior placebo-controlled
randomized trials. However, if characteristics in the current trial
differ from previous trials – for example, adherence to the active
control regimen is lesser or greater than planned – then the chance of a
false positive result (type I error) or a false negative result (type II
error) can be different than planned. In this work, we proposed a method
for rigorously adapting a non-inferiority trial based on observed
characteristics of the active control participants. This is joint work
with 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fredhutch.org/en/labs/profiles/donnell-deborah.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Deborah
Donnell&lt;/a&gt;,

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fredhutch.org/en/labs/profiles/hanscom-brett.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Brett
Hanscom&lt;/a&gt;,
and Jim Hughes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Broadly Neutralizing Antibodies</title>
      <link>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/project/bnabs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/project/bnabs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The broadly neutralizing antibody VRC01, developed by the Vaccine
Research Center of the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious
Diseases, is currently being evaluated in the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ampstudy.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Antibody Mediated
Prevention&lt;/a&gt; study (AMP). While the primary goal
of AMP is to assess the preventative efficacy of VRC01, a key secondary
goal is to determine if this efficacy differs based on characteristics
of the HIV virus. There are many possible locations on the HIV genome
that we might be interested in; if we simply did a statistical test for
association at each possible location, and then appropriately accounted
for this multiple testing, then we would have low power to detect
effects. To prepare for AMP, we used data on HIV viruses from the

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hiv.lanl.gov/components/sequence/HIV/neutralization/main.comp&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Compile, Neutralize, and Tally NAb
Panels&lt;/a&gt;
database. Our goals were to: (i) develop a score that performed well for
predicting whether or not an HIV virus was sensitive to neutralization
by VRC01, and (ii) to identify groups of HIV genome features that were
important in predicting neutralization sensitivity. This project is
joint work with 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/camagaret/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Craig Magaret&lt;/a&gt;,

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.benkeserstatistics.com/#!&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;David Benkeser&lt;/a&gt;, Peter Gilbert,
and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We next extended the methods used for the VRC01 analysis to combinations
of antibodies – a prevention strategy involving multiple bnAbs is likely
to be much more effective than a strategy with a single bnAb. Sohail
Nizam joined the team for this project. The software is implemented as a
Docker container.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A unified approach for inference on algorithm-agnostic variable importance</title>
      <link>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/publication/preprint/vim2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/publication/preprint/vim2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this work, we extended our approach from the R-squared variable importance measure to handle nonparametric extensions of many interesting measures, including the difference in classification accuracy, the difference in area under the receiver operating characteristic curve, and the difference in deviance. We also propose a test for the null hypothesis of zero importance that has proper type I error control.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A multi-view model for relative and absolute microbial abundances</title>
      <link>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/publication/preprint/paramedic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bdwilliamson.github.io/publication/preprint/paramedic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this work, we propose a statistical method for combining inexpensive
(but often lower-quality) estimates of relative abundance (e.g.,
collected using universal primers for the 16S rRNA gene) and higher
quality (but often expensive) estimates of absolute abundance (e.g.,
from quantitative PCR) to estimate absolute abundance of all taxa.
Crucially, our proposal accounts for differences in the efficiency of
taxon detection in the relative and absolute abundance data. This is
joint work with 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://faculty.washington.edu/jphughes/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jim Hughes&lt;/a&gt;
and 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://statisticaldiversitylab.com/team/amy-willis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Amy Willis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
